Finding aid for the J. Paul Getty Trust Press Releases and Public Outreach Materials, 1954-1959, 1973-2022 (bulk 1983-2022) IA10011
Institutional Records and Archives
J. Paul Getty Trust press releases and public outreach materials
1954-1959,
1973-2022
(bulk 1983-2022)
Institutional Records and Archives
J. Paul Getty Trust. Communications Department
J. Paul Getty Trust. Public Affairs Department
J. Paul Getty Museum. Department of Public Information and Visitor Services
IA10011
28.46 Linear Feet (50 boxes)
2.2026 GB (2,483 files)
The records comprise press releases, event calendars, magazines published by the Getty, presentations to the press and public, and other materials created and disseminated by the J. Paul Getty Museum and the J. Paul Getty Trust, 1954-1959 and 1973-2022 (bulk 1983-2022). The records contain analog and digital files documenting the events and activities the Getty wished to publicize to the media and the public.
Appraisal
Duplicate materials were weeded to the extent possible; however, some duplication is to be expected.
Accruals
The Institutional Archives regularly receives public relations materials from the Getty Communications Department. These are integrated into this guide at regular intervals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records in this finding aid originated in accessions 1986.IA.56, 2001.IA.06, 2007.IA.06, 2007.IA.10, 2007.IA.34, 2010.IA.26, 2013.IA.66, 2014.IA.16, 2015.IA.03, 2016.IA.03, 2016.IA.28, 2017.IA.03, 2018.IA.03, 2018.IA.15, 2019.IA.03, 2020 .IA.04, 2021.IA.04, 2021.IA.29, and 2022.IA.04.
Restrictions on Access
All records described in this finding aid are available for use by qualified researchers.
The following records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
These records comprise press releases, press kits, event calendars, magazines, reports, recordings, and advertisements. Records were created and published by the J. Paul Getty Museum and the J. Paul Getty Trust and date from 1954 to 1959 and 1973 to 2022 (bulk 1983-2022). The collection includes original, photocopied, and digital (.pdf, .mht, .mhtml, and MP3) files. The materials, intended to publicize Getty events and activities to the media and the public, were disseminated by the J. Paul Getty Museum (1954-1982), the Department of Public Affairs (1983-1999), and the Communications Department (2000-present). The organization issued relatively few press releases until the construction of the Villa Museum in 1974, and it is uncertain if any exist from 1960 to 1972. An increase in press release production came in the early 1980s with the expansion of the trust and its operations.
Subjects include acquisitions; administration; awards, including Getty Medal recipients; building projects; collaborative projects; cultural property conservation and restoration; exhibitions; grant awards; logistical advisories; organizational initiatives; publication announcements; public and scholarly events; senior personnel and board of trustees appointments; and others. Of note are the J. Paul Getty Museum 1954 opening press release, transcriptions of news articles regarding the opening that were published in local media outlets, opening day remarks, and event flow for the opening day reception; and various press kits documenting the building of the Getty Center in Brentwood, including site and architect selection, center design, construction, and the 1997 opening. All Getty programs, including those no longer in operation, are represented.
While the number of materials in this collection is extensive, it is not presumed that they are comprehensive for any given subject or year, excepting digital press releases dating 2016 to 2022.
Organization
These records are organized into six series:
Series I. Chronological press releases, 1954-1959, 1973-2022
Series II. Press releases, subject files, 1974-2002, 2006
Series III. Press kits, 1954, 1973, 1983-1984, 1989-2020
Series IV. Calendars, 1988-1991, 1999, 2016-2022
Series V. Magazines, reports, and recordings, 1986-1997, 2012-2022
Series VI. Advertisements, 1997-2004.
Administrative History
The J. Paul Getty Trust's origins date to 1953, when J. Paul Getty established the J. Paul Getty Museum as a California charitable trust to house his growing art collections. Originally a small, private institution located in Mr. Getty's ranch house near Malibu, the museum moved to the newly constructed Villa in grounds adjacent to the ranch house in 1974. When most of Mr. Getty's personal estate passed to the trust in 1982, the trustees decided that given the size of the endowment, it should make a greater contribution to the visual arts and humanities than the museum could alone. Out of this resolve grew an expanded commitment to the arts in the general areas of scholarship, conservation, and education. This took the shape of new programs including the Center for the History of Art and Humanities (GCHAH), Art History Information Institute (AHIP), Conservation Institute, Grant Program, and Center for Education in the Arts (GCEA). Smaller programs include the Museum Management Institute (MMI), a joint venture with the Art Museum Association of America, and the Program for Art on Film, a joint venture with the Metropolitan Museum of Art. In 1983 the trust's corporate name was changed from the J. Paul Getty Museum to the J. Paul Getty Trust to reflect its broader scope, with the museum becoming an operating program of the trust. On December 16, 1997 the Getty Center, a new unified facility housing all Getty programs, was opened in the Brentwood neighborhood of Los Angeles, CA.
As the trust matured several of the programs underwent administrative and functional reorganizations resulting in name changes or dissolutions. AHIP's name was changed to the Getty Information Institute (GII) in 1996 as part of a new identity program instituted by the Trust just prior to occupancy of their new unified facility. To avoid confusion with the soon-to-open Getty Center in Brentwood, GCHAH was renamed the Getty Research Institute for the History of Art and the Humanities in 1996. Three years later the program's name was shortened to the Getty Research Institute (GRI). The GII was dissolved in 1999 and many of its functions were absorbed by the Getty Research Institute (GRI). The Getty Center for Education in the Arts (GCEA) changed its name to the Getty Education Institute for the Arts (GEI) in 1996, and was disbanded in 1998. In 1996, Program for Art on Film was transferred to the Pratt Institute and the Trust ended its affiliation with the program. The Getty Leadership Institute (GLI) was created in 1996 to administer museum executive education programs, including the Museum Management Institute (MMI). Administration of GLI programs was transferred to the Claremont Graduate University in 2010. The Grant Program changed its name to the Foundation in January 2005.
J. Paul Getty Museum press material was prepared and distributed by Museum curator Paul Wescher from 1954-1959. Press release production was not officially institutionalized until 1974 with the creation of the Public Information department and the appointment of Deborah Ashin as Public Affairs Director, although some press releases are dated from 1973. From 1979 to 1997 museum press releases were consistently rendered from Public Information, and in 1983 the Department of Public Affairs was created to issue press releases on behalf of the J. Paul Getty Trust and its non-museum programs. The Department of Public Affairs reported directly to trust leadership, whereas Public Information reported to the museum. In 1998 the Department of Public Affairs began issuing press releases on behalf of the museum and responsibility for the organization's press release function was placed in a single department. The Department of Public Affairs name was changed to Communications in 2000. With the hiring of Pamela Johnson in August 2002, the department head role was elevated to the level of Vice President, reporting to the President and CEO.
Although the Communications department had been creating digital (.pdf files) press releases for some time, systematic annual collection of the materials by Institutional Archives began in 2015.
J. Paul Getty Museum and J. Paul Getty Trust Director of Public Affairs, and J. Paul Getty Trust Vice President, Communications include:
1974-1982: Deborah Ashin, Public Affairs Director
1983-1994: Phillipa Calnan, Public Affairs Director
1995-2001: Lori Starr, Public Affairs Director
2001-August 2002: Jill K. Murphy, Interim Head of Communications and President's Chief of Staff
August 2002-2005: Pamela Johnson, Vice President Communications
2005-July 2018: Ron Hartwig, Vice President Communications
September 2018-present: Lisa Lapin, Vice President Communications
Related Archival Materials Note
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the agencies and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Getty Institutional Archives
J. Paul Getty Museum Department of Public Information and Visitor Services Records, 1973-1981, 1984-1991, undated. J. Paul Getty Museum Department of Public Affairs. Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20007.
J. Paul Getty Trust Communications exhibition and programming publicity development records, 1989, 1997, 2000-2010. J. Paul Getty Trust Communciations Department. Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20041.
J. Paul Getty Trust Communications Department images, 1981-2005 (bulk 1990-1999), undated. J. Paul Getty Trust Communications Department. Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA30003.
J. Paul Getty Trust, Communications Department audio and video recordings, 1973-2004. J. Paul Getty Trust Communications Department. Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA30004.
J. Paul Getty Trust press clippings, 1954-2019, undated (bulk 1983-2019). J. Paul Getty Trust Communications Department. Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA30017.
Existence and Location of Copies
Final versions of hard-copy press releases issued by the Getty from 1954-1959 and 1973-2006 have been scanned, processed using uncorrected optical character recognition (OCR), and saved as .pdf-a files. The contents of each folder have been scanned as a single .pdf; depending on the contents of the folder each .pdf may be a single press release or multiple releases. The links to these electronic versions appear beneath the folder titles in the Series I. Chronological press releases, and Series II. Press releases, subject files inventory for the years 1954-1959 and 1983-2004; records dating 2005-2006 have been partially scanned. Internal word-searchability of the .pdf files varies depending on the consistency of the font and on the quality and background color of the original release. Please note that all material in the folders that was not a final Getty-issued press release was not scanned, including drafts, memos, correspondence, photos, and releases issued by other organizations.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access to digital files in 2014.IA.16, 2015.IA.03, 2016.IA.03, 2017.IA.03, 2018.IA.03, 2019.IA.03, 2020.IA.04, 2021.IA.04, and 2022.IA.04 is available online through the links provided in the inventory.
Nonprofit organizations -- Employees; Research institutes; Humanities -- Information technology; Museum trustees; Museums -- Acquisitions; Art -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Cultural property -- Conservation and restoration; Art -- Conservation and restoration; Art in education; Special events; Press releases; Nonprofit organizations; Museums -- Press coverage; Memorandums; Brochures; Calendars; Announcements; Art -- Exhibitions; Ephemera; Art museums -- Public relations; Exhibition announcements; Art museums -- Design and construction; Electronic documents; Magazines (periodicals); Advertising campaigns -- United States; Getty Conservation Institute; Getty Research Institute for the History of Art and the Humanities; Getty Center for Education in the Arts; Getty Education Institute for the Arts; Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities; Getty Art History Information Program; J. Paul Getty Museum; Program for Art on Film (New York, N.Y.); J. Paul Getty Trust; Getty Foundation; Getty Research Institute; Getty Foundation. Getty Leadership Institute; Getty Information Institute
- Chronological press releases, 1954-1959; 1973-2022; Series I.; 4.06 Linear Feet (8 boxes); 0.99 GB (2,249 files)
  Scope and Contents note
  These press releases in hardcopy and digital format document events that the J. Paul Getty Trust wished to publicize to media outlets and date from 1954 to 1959 and 1973 to 2022. The press releases, intended to promote Getty activities, were distributed to journalists and other members of the media by the J. Paul Getty Museum (1954-1982), the Department of Public Affairs (1983-1999), and the Communications Department (2000-present). Also present are media advisories, event calendars, and memos. Of note are the J. Paul Getty Museum 1954 opening press release, transcriptions of news articles regarding the opening that were published in local media outlets, opening day remarks, and event flow for the opening day reception.
  Topics include acquisitions; administration; awards, including Getty Medal recipients; building projects; collaborative projects; cultural property conservation and restoration; exhibitions; grant awards; logistical advisories; organizational initiatives; publication announcements; public and scholarly events; senior personnel and board of trustees appointments; and others. All Getty programs, including those no longer in operation, are represented. It is uncertain if any press releases exist from 1960 to 1972.
  A portion of press releases dating 2000-2006 were received in digital (.pdf) format; hardcopy duplicates may also be present. Starting in 2014 press releases were received in exclusively digital format; 2014-2021 press releases appear as .pdf files, and 2022 press releases appear in .mhtml format. Duplicate press releases may also appear in Series II. Press releases, subject files and Series III. Press kits.
  While the number of press releases is extensive, it is not presumed to be a comprehensive collection, except from 2016 to 2022.
  Organization
  The records are arranged into three sections: J. Paul Getty Museum, J. Paul Getty Trust, and J. Paul Getty Trust, digital materials. Records are arranged in chronological order, and chronological order by program.
  Press releases dating 1954-1959, 1973-2004, and a partial set dating 2005-2006 have been digitally scanned to a repository for access. None of the records dating 2007-2008 have been scanned. Links to access copies appear beneath the folder titles in the inventory.
  Digital press releases materials originating from the J. Paul Getty Trust, 2000-2022 are arranged in chronological order by program. Digital preservation requirements necessitate the bundling and processing of records by accession, so records are displayed in sets according to accession number and are not necessarily in strict chronological order. As a result date ranges prior to 2016 may be duplicated in the inventory headings instead of integrated under a single heading. Records dated 2016 and after are inventoried exclusively for that year. Note that some records may duplicate those found in the paper records press materials in this series, and in Series II. Press releases, subject files and Series III. Press kits.
  Digitized versions
  Final versions of hard-copy press releases issued by the Getty from 1954-1959 and 1973-2006 have been scanned, processed using uncorrected optical character recognition (OCR), and saved as .pdf-a files. The contents of each folder have been scanned as a single .pdf; depending on the contents of the folder each pdf may be a single press release or multiple releases. The links to these electronic versions appear beneath the folder titles in the inventory. Internal word-searchabiltiy of the .pdf files varies depending on the consistency of the font and on the quality and background color of the original release. Please note that all material in the folders that was not a final Getty-issued press release was not scanned,including drafts, memos, correspondence, photos, and releases issued by other organizations.
  Accruals note
  In 2015 Trust Communications began transferring press releases annually to Institutional Records and Archives in exclusively born-digital format, although selected hard-copy duplicates may appear in Series III. Press kits
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Access to digital files in 2014.IA.16, 2015.IA.03,2016.IA.03, 2017.IA.03, 2018.IA.03, 2019.IA.03, 2020.IA.04, 2021.IA.04, and 2022.IA.04 is available online through the links provided in the inventory.
  - J. Paul Getty Museum:
    - 1954 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 1)
      General note
      [Includes remarks and schedule of ceremonies for the 1954 opening]
    - 1955 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 2)
    - 1956 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 3)
    - 1958 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 4)
    - 1959 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 5)
    - 1973 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 6)
    - 1974 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 7)
    - 1975 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 8)
    - 1976 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 9)
    - 1977 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 10)
    - 1978 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 11)
    - 1979 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 12)
    - 1980 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 13)
    - 1981 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 14)
    - 1982 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 15)
  - J. Paul Getty Trust:
    - 1983 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 16)
    - 1984 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 17)
    - 1985 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 18A)
    - 1986 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 18B)
    - 1987 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 19)
    - 1988 (Box 1986.IA.56-1, Folder 20)
    - 1983-1988:
      - Art History Information Program, 1984-1985 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 22)
      - Art on Film, 1984; 1986-1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 23)
      - Building Program, 1983-1984; 1986-1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 24)
      - Conservation Institute, 1983; 1985-1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 25)
      - Center for the History of Art and the Humanities, 1983-1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 29)
      - Center for Education, 1985; 1987-1989 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 26)
      - Gifts, 1985-1988 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 27)
      - Grant Program, 1984-1985 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 28)
      - Museum, 1984; 1986,; undated (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 30)
      - Museum, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 31)
      - Museum Management Institute, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 32)
      - Trust, 1984-1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 33)
      - Other releases, 1985-1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 34)
      - Statements, 1986-1987 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 35)
    - 1989:
      - January-April 1989 (Box 1986.IA.56-2, Folder 1)
      - May-June 1989 (Box 1986.IA.56-2, Folder 2)
      - November-December 1989 (Box 1986.IA.56-2, Folder 3)
    - 1990: (Box 1986.IA.56-2, Folder 4)
    - 1991:
      - Art on Film (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 40)
      - Center for Education in the Arts (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 37)
      - Center for History of Arts and Humanities (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 39)
      - General, 1991 (Box 1986.IA.56-2, Folder 5)
      - Grant Program (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 38)
      - Museum (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 36)
      - Museum Management Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 41)
    - 1992:
      - Art History Information Program (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 45)
      - Art on Film (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 54)
      - Building Program (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 46)
      - Center for Education in the Arts (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 48)
      - Center for History of Arts and Humanities, January-March (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 53)
      - Center for History of Arts and Humanities, May-December (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 51)
      - Center for History of Arts and Humanities, April (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 52)
      - Conservation Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 47)
      - Grant Program (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 49)
      - Museum (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 42)
      - Trust (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 43)
      - Trust Statements (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 44)
    - 1993-1994:
      - Art History Information Program, 1993-1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 58)
      - Art on Film, 1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 5)
      - Center for History of Art and Humanities, 1993 (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 4)
      - Center for History of Art and Humanities, 1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 3)
      - Center for Education in the Arts, 1993-1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 60)
      - Conservation Institute, 1993-1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 59)
      - Gifts, 1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 57)
      - Grant Program, 1993 (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 2)
      - Grant Program, 1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 1)
      - Museum, 1993-1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 55)
      - Trust, 1993-1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-1, Folder 56)
      - Other releases, 1994 (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 6)
      - 1994 (Box 1986.IA.56-2, Folder 6)
    - 1995:
      - Art History Information Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 9)
      - Center for Education in the Arts (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 12)
      - Center for History of Art and Humanities (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 10)
      - Conservation Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 8)
      - General (Box 1986.IA.56-2, Folder 7)
      - Grant Program (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 13)
      - Museum (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 7)
      - Trust (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 11)
    - 1996:
      - Art History Information Program (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 16)
      - Center for Education in the Arts (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 18)
      - Center for History of Art and Humanities (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 17)
      - Conservation Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 15)
      - Grant Program (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 19)
      - Museum (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 20)
      - Trust (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 14)
    - 1997:
      - Conservation Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 21)
      - Education Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 25)
      - Grant Program (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 26)
      - Information Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 23)
      - Museum (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 27)
      - Research Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 24)
      - Trust (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 22)
    - 1998:
      - Conservation Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 28)
      - Education (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 29)
      - Grant Program (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 30)
      - Information Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 31)
      - Museum (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 34)
      - Research Institute (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 32)
      - Trust (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 33)
    - 1999:
      - Master list, (and a 3.5 inch floppy disc) (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 35)
      - January-March (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 36)
      - April-June (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 37)
      - July-September (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 38)
      - October-December (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 39)
    - 2000:
      - Master list (and a 3.5 inch floppy disc) (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 40)
      - January-April (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 41)
      - May-June (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 42)
      - August-September (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 43)
      - October-December (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 44)
      - Quarterly News Bulletins (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 45)
    - 2001:
      - January – April (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 46)
      - May-June (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 47)
      - July-August (Box 2007.IA.06-2, Folder 48)